"Caveats and Side Effects
of Taurine Supplements"
To taurine or not to taurine,
that's the question.
Taurine is an ingredient
in some so-called energy drinks,
which some people consume
to improve physical performance,
although there is
little evidence
that taurine per se
exerts any beneficial effects
in healthy individuals,
or animals,
without taurine depletion.
But that was written
before this seminal study,
published in one
of our most prestigious
scientific journals,
showing that
taurine supplementation
starting in middle-age
can significantly improve
the healthspan and lifespan
of a number
of different animals.
Now, not all animal studies
have shown benefit.
Lifelong
taurine supplementation
induced retardation
of learning
in mice, for example,
and low doses of taurine
significantly enhanced
lung tumor growth in mice,
which led the authors to suggest
that lung cancer patients
may want to stay away
from drinks with taurine.
You probably wouldn't want
to consume too much taurine
if you have
kidney failure either,
since taurine levels
are normally regulated
by our kidneys.
The acute symptoms
of taurine overload,
mainly dizziness,
were relatively mild
and rapidly disappeared
after stopping taurine,
but researchers suggested
there should be
warning-type labels
on beverages containing taurine
to caution patients
with kidney failure
from drinking them.
Similarly, patients
who have bleeding disorders
may not want to take taurine
since it might thin our blood.
Psoriasis patients
may also want to steer clear,
as taurine evidently causes
a predictable,
intense itching response
that can last a day or two,
making skin lesions worse.
It even caused the same reaction
in psoriasis patients
in remission.
Pregnant and lactating women
are pretty much encouraged
to stay away
from any and all supplements
not specifically
prescribed for pregnancy.
Similarly, individuals with
specific health conditions,
such as bipolar disorder,
epilepsy,
or kidney problems,
may want to be cautious.
The only bipolar
problem I could find
were a few case reports
of mania blamed on Red Bull.
This guy drank
20 cans of Red Bull,
that would make me manic too!
But, of course, Red Bull
has more than just taurine.
Caffeine alone may do it.
The epilepsy concern
may have to do with taurine
inhibiting detoxifying
enzymes in the liver
that are responsible
for breaking down
many commonly used drugs,
including anti-seizure drugs.
It could also be
because of adverse reactions
reported by some patients
with epilepsy
who took 1.5 grams a day,
including nausea, headache,
dizziness, nose-bleed,
and mild walking disturbances,
but the epilepsy
seemed incidental.
That may just be what sometimes
you see at higher doses.
Potential side effects
of excessive consumption
of taurine supplements
beyond recommended doses
includes
gastrointestinal disturbances,
such as nausea,
vomiting, and diarrhea,
and neurological symptoms,
like dizziness,
tremors, and headaches.
What are the recommended doses?
A proposed tolerated
upper safety limit
based on human clinical trials
is up to three grams a day,
but the longest trial
at that dose
was only up to four months.
In my last video,
I talked about a parallel
with another
conditionally non-essential
amino acid called arginine
that similarly looked good
in short-term trials,
but by six months appeared
to be killing people,
oopsie, so,
the study was shut down.
So, who knows
if the supposed safe level
of three grams a day
is actually safe?
The dose used in
that promising animal study
might be equivalent
to dosing people
with even more than that,
and higher doses
aren't necessarily better.
In this study on inflammation
and oxidative stress,
the lower doses,
three grams or less,
appeared to work better.
The thought is
that high doses of taurine
could downregulate
our own synthesis of taurine.
Why would that be a problem?
Well, our body makes taurine
from another amino acid
called cysteine.
So, if we're no longer
churning out taurine,
that may cause our levels
of cysteine to build up,
at least,
that's what happens in mice.
And that might be bad
because chronically high
levels of cysteine
have been closely associated
with a whole list
of disease states
including rheumatoid arthritis,
Parkinson's, Alzheimer's,
lupus, cardiovascular disease,
and adverse pregnancy outcomes.
On the other hand,
taurine may inhibit
our absorption
of another amino acid
called methionine,
since taurine and methionine
share the same
absorption transporter
through our intestinal lining.
That would be presumed
to be a good thing,
since lowering methionine intake
is considered
a feasible strategy
against chronic
and aging-related diseases,
as I discussed
in How Not to Age.
And, finally, the animal study
didn't address the impact of
taurine dietary supplementation
on the gut microbiome,
which I'll cover, next.